# Derek M. Walkama

Boston, MA (508)-273-3496 Derek.M.Walkama@gmail.com Data Scientist web: sites.tufts.edu/derekwalkama LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/derekwalkama

### Interests and Programming Languages

Data scientist currently working with causal ML in the target discovery space who is deeply interested in ML/AI, bioinformatics, causal and statistical modeling, and image analysis/processing. Have deep experience processing and modelling multi-omic data including: genomics (WGS), transcriptomics (NGS and single-cell), and EHR data.

#### Languages:

R iGraph, xts, gmlnet, caret, foreach, doParralel, tidyverse, seurat

Python numpy, scipy, pandas, tensorflow

Matlab image processing toolbox, curve fitting toolbox, parallel processing toolbox

unix StarCluster, ParallelCluster, AWS, BASH

## **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. Physics. Tufts University, 2021

Thesis: Elastic instability of flows and structures at low Reynolds number

Advisor: Professor Jeffrey S. Guasto

Sc.M. Physics. Tufts University, 2017

Graduated Magna Cum Laude

B.A. Physics & Mathematics Clark University, 2015

Graduated Cum Laude with Departmental Honors

#### Professional Experience

#### Senior Data Scientist, Early Development Feb 2022 - present

Aitia, Somerville, MA

- Oversaw the development of large scale, multi-modal causal models in multiple disease areas such as cancer, neurodegenerative, and cardiac. This includes the development of disease-specific multi-omic data pipelines.
- Led the design and development of a flagship model building pipeline that integrates an open-source data science tool, DVC (data version control), and proprietary causal AI software, REFS.
- Provided HPC support for platform migration from StarCluster to AWS ParallelCluster.

## Data Scientist, Early Development Feb 2021 - Feb 2022

Aitia, Somerville, MA

- Constructed Bayesian network models using proprietary Causal AI technology (REFS) to exploit the recent explosive growth of multi-omics and clinical data in order to create "virtual" (in silico) patients in oncology, neurodegeneration, and immunology.
- Disease specific data-sets with tens of thousands of features are curated and pre-processed for model building.
- Processed and modelled novel data such as "single-cell data" which is  $\sim 10,000 \times$  larger than standard transcriptomic data.

- Developed and supported tools for, and improvements to, the platform which are currently used by various departments allowing for future scalability.
- Presented important findings to both internal audiences and clients.

#### Graduate Research Assistant 2016 - 2021

Guasto Lab, Department of Mechanical Engineering, Tufts University, Medford, MA

- Currently studying localized stretching structures of viscoelastic fluids in porous media via DNA visualization techniques.
- Using particle tracking and Lagrangian statistical tools, discovered that dispersion is regulated by flow geometry in viscoelastic flows.
- Designed and conducted Monte-Carlo Langevin simulations of swimming cells in a viscosity gradient to support experimental discoveries.
- Discovered that disordering flow geometry affects the local flow type experienced by viscoelastic fluids and hinders a critical flow instability responsible for chaotic velocity fluctuations.
- Utilizing high speed microscopy, invertebrate sperm flagellum buckling was studied in a microfluidic extensional flow. An in-house flagella tracking algorithm was developed to investigate flagellum curvature.

#### Data Science Consultant Jan 2020 - Sept 2020

Gene Network Sciences Inc, Cambridge, MA

- Curated real-world financial and weather data was processed and vetted to build causal and predictive models using a proprietary causal machine learning platform (REFS).
- Identified quality issues with customer-provided data by developing a bespoke outlier detection algorithm, leading to customer modification of their internal data pipelines.
- Using repeated & stratified cross-validation, demonstrated value of integrating customer data with multi-modal financial data for building predictive models and assisting with go/no-go decisions for modeling.
- Findings were reported to clients and executives via intuitive graph visualizations (iGraph) and presentations. Described technical methods to lay audiences.

#### CERTIFICATIONS

2023

Key Topics in Causal Inference, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health Workshop given by leaders in the field of Causal Inference: Jamie Robbins, Miguel Hernán, Judith Lok, Eric Tchetgen Tchetgen, and Tyler Vanderweele.

#### Honors and Awards

2020 Burlingame Fellowship in Physics, Tufts University

Recognizes outstanding achievement by senior graduate student in Physics.

2018 Tufts Polymer Art Competition Winner

# JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- 1. D.M. Walkama, N. Waisbord, M. Kumar, A. Ardehkani, and J.S. Guasto. Geometry regulates dispersion in viscoelastic porous media flows. *In preparation for submission* (2023).
- 2. M. Stehnach, N. Waisbord, D.M. Walkama, and J.S. Guasto. Viscotaxis Aggregation of swimming cells in non-uniform viscous environments. *Nat. Phys.* 17, 926–930 (2021).
- 3. D.M. Walkama, N. Waisbord, and J.S. Guasto. Disorder suppresses chaos in viscoelastic flows. *Physical Review Letters* **124**, 164501 (2020).

- 4. M. Kumar, D.M. Walkama, J.S. Guasto, and A.M. Ardekani. The buckling of sperm flagellum in an extensional flow. *Physical Review E* **100**, 063107 (2019).
- 5. N. Waisbord, N. Stoop, D.M. Walkama, J. Dunkel, and J.S. Guasto. Anomalous percolation flow transition of yield stress fluids in porous media. *Physical Review Fluids* 4, 063303 (2019).

#### Contributed Presentations

- 1. B. Nathasingh, <u>D.M. Walkama</u>, L.M. Mayhew, K. Loh, J. Latourelle, B.W. Church, Y.E. Wang. AACR 2023. Orlando, Florida
  - "Infer cancer cell gene dependency in multiple myeloma using causal AI in-silico patient model"
- 2. D.D. Vagie, <u>D.W. Walkama</u>, L.M. Mayhew, T.E. Oakland, B.W Church. ASH Meeting 2022. New Orleans, Louisiana
  - "Causal ai in silico patient model identifies minichromosome (MCM) Family Genes as novel predictors for overall survival in multiple myeloma"
- 3. D.W. Walkama, N. Waisbord, J.S. Guasto. APS-DFD Meeting 2019. Seattle, WA "Geometric disorder regulates dispersion in viscoelastic porous media flows"
- 4. D.W. Walkama, N. Waisbord, J.S. Guasto. APS March Meeting 2019. Boston, MA "Disorder suppresses chaotic viscoelastic flow"
- D.W. Walkama, N. Waisbord, J.S. Guasto. APS-DFD Meeting 2018. Atlanta, GA "Disorder suppresses viscoelastic instability"
- 6. D.W. Walkama, N. Waisbord, J.S. Guasto. Tufts Polymer Research Symposium 2018. Medford, MA. "Disorder suppresses viscoelastic instability" (Poster)
  - \* Polymer art competition winner
- 7. D.W. Walkama, N. Waisbord, J.S. Guasto. New England Complex Fluids Workshop 2017. Boston, MA "geometric disorder suppresses elastic turbulence"
- 8. D.W. Walkama, N. Waisbord, J.S. Guasto. New England Complex Fluids Workshop 2017. Medford, MA "pattern formation in viscoelastic flow through porous media"

#### Teaching & Mentoring

#### **Assistant Teaching**

2016 fall PHY-0042, Electricity & Magnetism I, Course Assistant
2016 summer PHY-0042, Electricity & Magnetism I, Recitation Instructor
2016 spring PHY-0012, General Physics II, Lab Instructor
2015 fall PHY-0011, General Physics I, Lab Instructor

# Research Mentoring and Training

Mentored one undergraduate and one graduate students on independent research topics and provided training on microfabrication, microfluidics, microscopy, and image analysis.

## Professional Service and Society Membership

#### Journal Peer Review

Conducted peer review for submissions to: Soft Matter, Science Advances, and Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.

## Society Membership

- 1. Graduate Physics and Astronomy Student Society (President, 2017)
- 2. American Physical Society Division of Fluid Dynamics (APS-DFD)
- 3. New England Complex Fluids Workgroup (NECFW)

## References

# Professor Jeffrey S. Guasto

Tufts University

Medford, Massachusetts, USA

Associate Professor of Mechanical Engineering

Ph.D. Advisor

email: Jeffrey.Guasto@tufts.edu

## Dr. Jignesh Parikh

J Square Labs

Greater Boston Area, Massachusetts, USA

Founder

Supervisor and lead Computational Scientist

email: jiggy@jsquarelabs.com

# Dr. Laurel Mayhew

Aitia

Somerville, MA

Senior Director, Early Development

Supervisor

email: LMayhew.Career@gmail.com

## Dr. Daniel Vagie

Aitia

4

Somerville, MA

Data Scientist

R&D colleague

email: vagiedd@outlook.com